[Music]
so in the last few days as we see what
started in Minneapolis and then went to
Atlanta and Seattle and then everywhere
in the US it's interesting how consuming
a new cycle can make the most concerning
issue of three days ago almost
completely absent in people's minds and
attention but you also lose almost all
perspective if that happens so it's
important to kind of pay attention to
the sequence of things and the narrative
arc and the things that are not
forefront in the attention cycle so
right before the racial violence became
forefront we were seeing in the US and
escalation towards violence there was
very left-right oriented between red
state blue state having different focus
around how they were going to open and
it was kind of showing up as the mask
wears versus the non mask wears and we
saw armed people going to Capitol
buildings in protest of quarantine and
shut down we also started to see an
increase in racial focus in the news
over the week leading up to the case in
Minneapolis that set it all off and I'm
not gonna say like a single narrative of
some central command and control
function that I think is orchestrating
everything but I'm gonna mention
anomalies that I think you should be
paying attention to so we see the case
of the man who was jogging and the
retired cop and his son shot him that
was like a week before and then we see
increased news of white supremacy and a
lot more images of white guys with guns
at Capitol buildings then we see in
relationship to the guy who was running
and got shot and there were protests
black open carry of weapons associated
with the protests and then also black
open carry of weapons taking
escorting a black lawmaker to the
courthouse or some state building and
then we see Joe Biden's comments about
you ain't black and like just a whole
bunch of increase in race attention in
primary news cycles and then we see the
case with George Floyd so there's a big
question for me of like did we just have
a particular unusually racist week or
does the new cycle not actually reflect
the background rate of things for other
reasons and for it for every situation
like we see with George Floyd the number
of those that aren't caught like it's
just um it's just a much less rare
phenomena than I think most people think
it is sadly I think most black people in
inner cities know it's not as rare a
phenomena so then we see the video
circulating that the we see this guy
with a hammer and black tactical gear
breaking the windows of the autozone
right in Minneapolis and we see people
jumping to thinking assessing that he's
a cop as an agent provocateur or that he
is a antifa guy or a white supremacist
or a Soros agent there's a lot of
different hypotheses but a lot of images
are surfacing of the buildings being set
on fire and the windows being broken by
white people at the black protest
rallies that were not breaking like me
and the initial movement to property
destruction and violence was not
actually then and broken windows theory
is very clear that once like who ones
the first Molotov cocktails thrown and
it becomes much easier to engage in
throwing Molotov cocktails once the
first windows are broken because there's
like a threshold to move past that that
has already been broken and so the idea
that
police officers or people with other
agendas infiltrate a protest group that
is otherwise peaceful and throw the
first rock to justify use of police
force on the other side like that's a
very well-known phenomenon but right now
we can hypothesize a lot of groups that
would have a motive to do it for a lot
of reasons so some people either are
buying the standard narrative or they're
too quickly jumping to the alternate
narrative of it was the cop for this
reason or it was the white supremacists
trying to blame the black guys or it was
the deep state Hillary Clinton Joe Biden
supporting liberals that are trying to
create incite more reason to have people
stay at home than the quarantine already
was to move towards their goal to steal
an election there's like a gazillion
hypotheses I think the problem is the
people who aren't buying the mainstream
media narrative are buying the first
alternate narrative that appeals to
their sense making desire to not have
uncertainty and put the pieces together
before there's adequate evidence that
that alternate narrative is actually
much better so the guy who broke the
windows was definitely not a normal part
of the protest but I don't know who he
was an agent for or what the motive was
because the data that suggests any of
the 10 different hypotheses are not
solid yet so one of the things I'm
wanting to encourage is don't let your
attention cycle be controlled by the
attention cycle of your social media
feed or your mainstream news that's one
thing the other thing is be very careful
about how easy it is to get induced into
being on one side of groupthink and
conflict theory let's talk about
conflict theory for a moment it's
there's a few types of natural cleaving
x' or easy cleaving Ziff not natural
where it's very easy to drive conflict
between people political left-right is a
very easy one you can do red state blue
state stuff you can do they have a make
America
again hat versus a rainbow gay flag at
like they're they're literally wearing
flags of different kinds to symbolize
red shirt blue shirt right like the type
type of team they're in and then you can
drive conflict between them which both
creates a sense of clear sense making of
I know who my team is I know what my
might the group think of the narrative
on my side it is and so red blue is very
easy people versus the cops is very easy
race issues are very easy races may be
the easiest because it's where the flag
is biologically built-in if everybody
here has not studied conflict theory
you're gonna have a hard time making
sense of the world without a good model
of how conflict arises between people
how it gets intentionally stirred up how
people resolve it and there's a lot of
difference schools of conflicts area
that are worth studying but at a minimum
everybody should know Rene Gerard's work
and I'm not saying that I agree with
Gerard there are things that he said
that we're extremely insightful so
specifically his idea is that the
fundamental nature of conflicts comes
from the fact that desire is mimetic
meaning that we learn to want stuff the
same way we learn language by watching
other people and that I don't know
Mandarin and I don't know so he Lee and
I don't know Dutch because I didn't
watch people speaking those I watch
people speak in English so I got
conditioned to think in a world view
through aesthetic frames through like
it's very deep how much my whole
identity and everything was conditioned
by what I watched so his arguments is
that much of what we want is also
conditioned by watching people and so we
end up in Nate Lee wanting what other
people have which means that desire and
extra Blee drives conflict somebody
people
have stuff you want that thing more
similar kinds of things then as more
people are wanting the same things and
conflicting over it the conflict itself
becomes mimetic people learn through
mimesis to identify with the zionist or
the anti-zionist side based on which
side of the wall they grew up on or the
you know whatever the conflict they
happen to have been born into and then
in Gerard's model the conflict continues
to increase until there's so much
embodied energy that you're gonna get
something like a war and the least
violent way to deal with it is to have a
scapegoat a sacrificial rather than a
all against all war be able to have some
sacrificial person that everybody gets
that is able to be effectively blamed
for the whole scenario and then we're
able to take them out and decrease the
embodied conflict energy for a while
then the cycle has to repeat jords work
really says that there is no there
historically has been no way out of that
and the role of various religions was to
figure out how to do scapegoating well
and that that's what all of the
sacrifices of various religious
traditions were about that Christianity
was actually trying to get rid of
scapegoating by showing the person they
scapegoated was actually innocent - not
only innocent with the highest kind of
innocence so that the way people would
get out of his answer actually of how
you get out of scapegoating was everyone
developed christ-like virtues but
specifically as critique said that by
getting rid of religion and this is
relevant to the goals of this group that
is trying to reinvent of human virtue by
getting rid of religion we got rid of
the way of dealing with the mimetic
conflict while simultaneously getting
much much larger weapons of destruction
so that rather than have things heat up
in Europe and kill a Jew sacrificially
it had to be this massive kind of
killing of all of these Jews and so
okay so why am i bringing that up I
think it's very easy to I think there
are lots of reasons to want to drive
conflict and to want to keep groups of
people having attention focused in
different ways maybe this is actually
the way I'll talk about it
power pretty much translates to power
over other people to have power over
their behaviors whether I want people to
vote for me in a particular way or I
want them to buy my stuff or I want them
to publicly support my ideas I need to
control other people's behavior to
control their behavior I need to control
their minds and so warfare is main
mainly not fought with bullets like the
kinetic warfare that we think of as
warfare that's fought with weapons is
maybe 1% of warfare 99% of warfare is
diplomatic warfare political warfare
economic warfare narrative warfare
information warfare all of this comes
together to what we call hybrid warfare
or really just politics or game theory
or the game of power but but think of it
as high hybrid or population centric
warfare
so in this war the treasure being fought
over is people's minds and the
battleground is people's minds the
primary weapons are tools the tools of
narrative influence and emotionally
vacation and control of the information
flows and in these wars they're
asymmetric wars because you have some
actors that have access to billion or
trillion-dollar level information
technologies and ki empowered micro
targeting and then you have other people
are just
to figure shit out on their own and they
don't even know they're in a war and
they don't even know that their own mind
is the battleground of the war and they
think they believe the shit they believe
and they think they came to it on their
own they think they're doing a good job
sense making and they don't realize that
as they're researching of the trillions
of pages of shit they could see the ones
that they will ever even be able to see
based on what shows up in their YouTube
feed or their Google search or
manipulated by algorithms that have
agendas behind them as well as the
original source material of whoever put
it out for which reasons ok so zooming
out from the current violence for
moments we have an election coming up in
the u.s. that will be radically
consequential for the world either way
no matter who wins currently whether the
election is illegally tampered with and
stolen or not half of the population
will think it was this is a real problem
right
because what happens when a third to a
half of the population no matter which
way it goes thinks that it was stolen
and thinks it was radically
consequential well like one of two
really bad things happens either the
people get violent much more so than we
currently have and that sets off one
whole cascade of scenarios where they
don't get violent and the people who
want to steal elections get even clearer
that they just can with impunity so
we're like fuck what do we do with this
moving forward now mail-in ballots our
mail-in ballots easier to corrupt than
in-person voting yep totally a & Co vid
as one reason violence could be another
but co vid is one reason to have mail-in
ballots like might there be reasons
associated with that yeah now might
there be reasons that people who really
want Trump out of office would want to
initiate things
that make Trump look worse and that say
look at all the bad shit that's
happening during Trump we could also
talk about what motive the Trump
campaign would have to be engaged in
something where you wouldn't want
transfer of power to occur so I'm not
there's a there's a version of this that
is easy to buy for either political
leaning I don't find that most
successful politicians that I have
encountered near the top of the power
actually believe red vs. blue ideology
they just believe in the game of power
and they signal red vs. blue ideology as
part of their mimetic warfare to control
the people that are going to vote for
them just like I don't think most of the
people that end up engaging religions
and holy wars at the most strategic
level really even are religious I think
they know that these are ways to get
people to do things for reasons that are
mostly strategic as we look at war a
little bit more and we look at the
tension heating up on the India China
border it's such a big deal like what's
happening there and the India China
Pakistan interaction and the India China
Russia interaction and as we look at it
with kovat related stuff obviously what
what happens to the spread of the virus
with all of the protests that are
definitely not social distancing well
we'll find out what happens when like
with Germany and South Korea and China
who started to get second waves of
infection after reopening what happens
when we start to get second waves here
and the political tension is so heated
around the idea of closing again and
then we also start to see things like
because of the Cova chat down of
transportation the food supply system
got radically damaged right giver
take the food supply for two billion
people got damaged and so Nigeria has a
25 million person in secure food
population that all went from food
insecure to actually don't have food and
now violence has been raising on the
ground both insurgencies local crime and
Boko Haram that's probably going to
trigger an exodus and a massive refugee
situation but after Syria it's like
where do the refugees go
so then what it what comes from that
conflict why so we're definitely at a
unique moment in the world we are at a
moment where because of the
connectedness of supply chains because
of the ability for viruses in airplanes
to move around the world so fast because
of the ability of news cycles to move so
fast so we go from an event in
Minneapolis to in every city because of
because of those things the inner
connection for the cascade of events
from anywhere to everywhere and from one
sector to other sectors is so high on
top of systemic fragility on top of very
high embodied emotional energy this next
phase of time is going to see a
continuance of a cascade of very serious
problems how do we make sense of the
world given all of these dynamics and
how do we respond
I always feel stuck when someone asks me
there how do we for some very large
audience have we respond because it's
gonna be very different based on
people's skills and capacities and
interests there's not like a very good
generalized answer to that
like David how are you responding well
you're trying to both put out
information that helps people and share
frames that help people process
information and maybe that helps them
get less emotionally hijacked so they
can have some more clarity like those
seem like within your bailiwick of
things to do that you can do super
important things that need done
there's gonna be an equivalent of that
in totally different ways that everyone
on here has as a possibility so I think
people recognizing that they actually
have some choice and where they put
their attention and some choice in the
meaning they make so both where they
focus and actually they have choice and
where they put their attention they have
choice in the process of coming to
belief are they just kind of letting
themselves by the conclusions put in
front or are they really asking that am
I sure of this how would I be sure of
this because they're going there's going
to be a response to their own sense of
certainty or uncertainty and they also
have some choice in the meaning they
make around the things and all this is
gonna affect their state so it means
it's overwhelm is something someone
really has a choice to indulge or not
and so sometimes I'll notice that
there's so much coming in and I'm like
what the fuck do I do about this and
there's a beginning impulsive
overwhelmed and I know I I'm not trying
to pretend or repress it but I also know
that going into an overwhelm
is not useful and I have a kind of deep
commitment to be useful so I have a deep
commitment to want to think about things
in a way that allows me to continue to
respond so I'll be like okay well let's
just step back and actually write down
what are all the things that I see going
on let's make a situational assessment
map right let's so rather than just
start to spiral into something like let
me start to identify what are the knowns
what are the unknowns what are the
things I might be able to do something
about where I want to put more of my
sense making into that area because I
might actually have some agency in that
area so some people on here that will
what is theirs to do will be largely
around serving their local communities
but you know
other people might have might work in
the finance sector and have specific
things that they can do that are
particularly meaningful to be able to
get the right types of projects funded
or yeah I don't know what I can say not
to do right is definitely make sure okay
here's an important one I'll say one
thing to do
understand the basics of strategy if
you're gonna try and do anything so that
you don't just make sure it worse or be
totally useless so strategy 101 every
response everything that you do if
you're effective some people will not
like and it will evoke a counter
response factor the counter response in
what you're doing and see if it's still
a good idea if you are not factoring
counter responses you are not doing
strategy you're just being reactive now
you might be super righteous in your
reactivity but you that doesn't mean
that you are actually a pawn that is
being manipulated by forces that are
doing strategy you aren't actually doing
strategy and so if you're wanting to do
something to make sure Trump doesn't get
reelected or to make sure that systemic
racism gets addressed or whatever it is
you just have to think in this
particular action who that will feel
threatened by this will counter respond
in what ways and what resources are
available to them
and if I'm escalating the game right if
I'm increasing the war on one side
driving an arms race of escalation am i
driving it in the right direction do
that if you aren't doing that then
you're most likely escalating things in
the wrong direction
you're doing guess listening to you I
mean we've done quite a lot of
conversations around
I think phase shift for Humanity was the
first one where you talked about the
self terminating nature of the current
dynamic and I guess it's one thing to
talk about that and to have seen it as a
possibility it's another one when you
feel it on a kind of visceral level and
I wonder I just wonder whether you
because you talk I mean you use some
beautiful metaphors about the
caterpillar and the butterfly and I'd
say for talking about kind of phase
shift and self terminating systems you
actually sketch out quite a sort of
positive vision as well has that changed
or you each still no it hasn't changed I
think that everything that's happening
right now was going to happen some
version of it there's a lot of path
dependencies if it didn't have to have
Cove it as a path and it could have been
a different pandemic or it could have
been grid collapse or it could have been
climate change driving refugees driving
a war there's a gazillion things that
could have started the cysts the
systemic cascades but it was inevitable
which is why I like that's mostly what
I've talked about for the last six or
seven years was trying to have hope
people say that was inevitable let's see
what we can do to do anticipate ori good
good things if you identify every area
that there is a risk there is also a
meaningful upside and this is a way to
think about what might be yours to do
when an environmental niche gets
disturbed it's much easier to have new
things come in and change the process so
if we go through and look at all of the
areas where there are major problems and
where there are major risks and
say what is the system that's actually
breaking down and what would a better
version of that system be and what could
we do to implement those better versions
of the system rather than try to
reinstate the security of the old ones
that would be a beginning of thinking
about the opportunity space and we could
talk about that with global finance we
could talk about it with infrastructure
we could talk about it with the
healthcare system on and on write the
judicial reform all those things and
someone just posted this in the chat and
I think it's really true so far it seems
that the pandemic and the crisis is
accelerating all of the we're not in a
shift into a new system it seems to be
just accelerating and compounding all of
the worst aspects of the old one most
sense of of how that process might play
out and where where's the sort of hope
in that if there is any most people who
care about things widely care about the
global Commons long term suck at doing
things like they suck at doing things at
scale because most anyone is good at
doing things at scale one at the game of
power because to do things at scale
means to be able to influence things in
a way that will beat out competitors and
go against people who want things to go
otherwise so right now there's a lot of
people dirt like during the Cova time
there's a lot of people feeling like
they have more free time than ever but
the most powerful people in the world
have been busier than ever during this
time they have been consolidating the
market and buying up distressed assets
and massively increasing opportunism
during this time so one of the things I
would say
is necessary for it to be other than you
just said David is that the people who
actually are committed to the well-being
of humanity and the earth and
civilization long term must learn to be
how must learn how to be effective at
actually making things happen at a
global level do you like to ask your
question Roy yes what do you have to say
about yes the the resource of
cross-generational
mentoring and networking in in the
situation we're in it's complex it's
easy to say mmm cross generational
collaboration is good like it's it's
easy to say that diverse perspectives of
any kind being in conversation will
enrich everyone who is there that's true
the current situation that we're facing
the last times we face situations that
were relevantly analogous none of those
people are still alive in terms of the
generations that actually know anything
about it like the people who were in
World War 2 aren't still here the people
who were in the Great Depression aren't
still here the people who were in the
1918 plague aren't still here and this
is like if you study generational theory
like Straus how or you study Baudrillard
typically things repeat on the cycle
that once the people who had the
hard-won knowledge are dead we repeat
the thing because they're gone right so
part of the generational connection I
want people to do is study the work of
the people who really understood the
last relevant issues who happened to be
dead it might have been alive a little
while now there are still people who
were involved in in Vietnam and the
counterculture movement and who were
involved in different times that are
relevant and to discuss
so like I have a friend mark Stallman he
was involved during that generation but
he was doing intelligence work and like
he was working with Freeman Dyson
directly regarding what was brought to
JFK to do with Khrushchev that was a big
part of what's led to things broke down
there so there's knowledge that he has
firsthand that super directly relevant
but like when I look at the
counterculture movement as a whole and I
look at the Green Revolution and the
sexual revolution and the Civil Rights
process and the women's rights all the
various things the deeper story that I
see most of the activists who were there
don't know the deeper story I see is
like actually understanding COINTELPRO
and how the FBI CIA and other
intelligence agencies actually
infiltrated the the progressive
movements to very specifically derail
them and get them focused on shift it
would be an effective that is that we're
still doing today
so I happen to believe that there was
intentional up regulation by those power
structures of post-modernism as a
structure of thought because if the
people who studied social science only
studied how to critique the game of
power without actually knowing how to
effectively organize then it would make
sure that they never could actually
really do anything so if every time
someone's organizing well you call it
imperialism you won't end up organizing
well becoming an imperialist so you'll
just be noise and that's fine and the
social sciences that are like actually
studying the history of military theory
and political theory and and strategy
itself
got very downregulated in exchange for
something that would make people feel
more righteous while being less
effective and so I want to make sure
that we're learning the right lessons
from the right periods of history so
what I would say is that when I think
about generations and I take all the
generations that are alive now I would
say that 99% of the people in all those
generations have been the victims of
intentional disinformation and a mostly
just all confused so we can have
intergenerational sharing of some
confused generations with others it's
still nice to have different
perspectives but I would mostly like for
people to have more clear and incisive
insight at all and across a longer time
period than their own experience a
deeper study of history and like that
so I was just wondering what you know
where you feel stuck and you feel like
you're kind of in a hopeless situation
making space for grief so emotions of
all kind can influence our sense making
they can also influence our choice
making I want we all know what it's like
to have emotions that are not being
clearly processed influenced our choice
making in damaging ways right reacting
out of anger or whatever but then we can
also say ok so I don't want to be
reactive emotionally so I'm going to
suppress emotions and pretend to do like
do a bad version of Stoicism
and just numb down emotional
intelligence in which case I'm taking
one whole type of information one whole
way of sense making and turning it off
and you could call emotion um this is
reductive but I'm just saying one lens
you could call emotion a way of being
able to read
data partly our emotion is responding to
the situation partly our emotion is
responding to the narrative we make of
the situation so in terms of the
narrative we make that's where we want
to do CBT or DBT or Byron Katie's the
work or Krishnamurti inquiry it's a see
where did I make up some meaning that
fucked me up but then there are some
times where it's like if I see a cop
kneeling on someone's neck and killing
them and I don't feel angry something is
wrong with me like that's not about
meaning-making
I actually try and say no I'm only upset
because if meaning-making means I have
to instantiate a metaphysics where
nothing matters and then say well I'm
meaning made well yes I have a
metaphysics where things matter and in a
metaphysics where anything matters then
if the sacred is being harmed I can feel
pissed off I can feel sad I can feel
scared right so you know I'm kind of
inundated in data about catastrophic
risk so the most fucked up things all
the time and so it doesn't have the same
emotional response immediately that it
did the first time that I was exposed to
it but I still will just sit back put my
computer down and just cry when I think
about what's fucking happening in
Nigeria or when I think about what's
about to happen or because if I don't I
will actually have to dead in something
and then I become less sensitive which
means my sensing decreases and the
wholeness of self decreases so yeah you
you neither want to let you neither want
to repress the emotions and not listen
to them and learn from them nor do you
want to just unconsciously act on them
you want to incorporate that into a
[Music]
a way that you're connecting to and
making sense of reality this was one of
the talks from the rebel wisdom festival
a dozen more films from the festival are
available in our members area from John
Devaki Jordan Hall Nora Bateson Jamie
wheal Douglas rushkoff and many more so
become a rebel wisdom member and get
access to loads of exclusive films and
joined the rebel wisdom community for
cents making calls our wisdom Jim and
more we're also running our online
course again soon since making 101 with
faculty including Daniel Shmack Tim
burger check out the website for more
you